<project cat='proj'>
  <title>Jenkins Continuous Integration for FreeBSD</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Craig</given>
	<common>Rodrigues</common>
      </name>

      <email>rodrigc@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>R. Tyler</given>
	<common>Croy</common>
      </name>

      <email>tyler@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Li-Wen</given>
	<common>Hsu</common>
      </name>

      <email>lwhsu@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Steve</given>
	<common>Kreuzer</common>
      </name>

      <email>skreuzer@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Steve</given>
	<common>Wills</common>
      </name>

      <email>swills@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>jenkins-admin team</name>
      <email>jenkins-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>FreeBSD testing</name>
      <email>freebsd-testing@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="https://jenkins.FreeBSD.org">Jenkins CI server in FreeBSD cluster</url>
    <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Jenkins#Jenkins_for_FreeBSD_status">Jenkins on FreeBSD project status</url>
    <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Jenkins#Presentations_and_Working_Groups">Video and slides of March 13, 2014 presentation at Bay Area FreeBSD User Group (BAFUG)</url>
    <url href="http://jenkins-ci.org">Jenkins Continuous Integration</url>
    <url href="http://www.ansible.com">Ansible</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>Jenkins is a framework that is used by many companies and open source
       projects for Continuous Integration (CI).  CI allows developers
       to commit code to a Source Code Management (SCM) system such as
       Subversion, and then have automated programs check out,
       build, and test the code.  Jenkins is implemented in the Java
       language.</p>.

    <p>Ed Maste reviewed some CI work that Craig Rodrigues had done for the
       FreeNAS project with Jenkins, and encouraged Craig to
       set up something similar for the FreeBSD project.
       With the help of the FreeBSD cluster administration team,
       Craig set up a FreeBSD machine running two bhyve virtual machines,
       jenkins-9.FreeBSD.org and jenkins-10.FreeBSD.org.  Craig set up
       software builds of CURRENT and several stable branches
       on these machines.  The status of these builds is visible via
       a web interface which is accessible via jenkins.FreeBSD.org
       (which is an alias for jenkins-9.FreeBSD.org).  When any of these
       builds fail, e-mails are sent to freebsd-current@ or freebsd-stable@.
       E-mails are also sent directly to the list of people who
       recently committed code to Subversion since the last successful
       build.
    </p>

    <p>As part of the Jenkins setup, Craig encountered problems with
       running Java FreeBSD 9.2 and FreeBSD 10.0.  Both problems stemmed
       from changes to the FreeBSD Virtual Memory (VM) subsystem.
       On FreeBSD 9.2-RELEASE, running Jenkins under Java would cause the kernel to panic.
       This was a known problem, and fixed in 9.2.-RELEASE-p3.
       On FreeBSD 10.0-RELEASE, Java processes would randomly coredump.
       Disabling the <b>vm.pmap.pcid_enabled</b> sysctl seemed to fix
       the problem.  In PR 187238, Henrik Gulbrandsen submitted fixes to
       the FreeBSD VM to addrses this problem.  Konstantin Belousov
       committed these fixes to HEAD.  These fixes are being tested now.</p>

    <p>During the setup of the bhyve VM's which run Jenkins processes,
       Craig wrote scripts to start bhyve VM's from the rc.d bootup scripts.
       Craig committed those scripts to github.</p>  

    <p>On February 19, 2014, Craig sent a HEADSUP e-mail to developers@
       informing them that Jenkins was running in the FreeBSD cluster,
       and that they could look at the web interface to see the
       status of builds.</p>

    <p>On March 13, 2014, Craig gave a presentation of the Jenkins
       work at the Bay Area FreeBSD User Group (BAFUG) in Mountain View,
       California, U.S.A.  Video of the presentation was recorded
       and put online by iXsystems.</p>

    <p>Craig assembled a team of volunteers, jenkins-admin, to help
       maintain jenkins.FreeBSD.org and expand the use of Jenkins CI used
       in the FreeBSD cluster.  jenkins-admin consists of
       the following people working in the following areas:</p>

    <ul>
    <li>R. Tyler Croy is both a FreeBSD developer and a Jenkins developer.
       Tyler will be working
       on fixing bugs in Jenkins specific to FreeBSD.  Tyler is
       first looking at fixing the libpam4j library which is used
       by Jenkins to interface with the PAM system for user authentication.
       The released version of libpam4j does not currently work on FreeBSD.</li>

    <li>Li-Wen Hsu maintains the devel/jenkins port.
       Li-Wen set up a Jenkins build which rans the scan-build
       static analyzer which is part of LLVM.</li>

    <li>Steve Kreuzer has experience administering Jenkins systems.
       Steve set up several builds on jenkins.FreeBSD.org, including
       a Jenkins build of the FreeBSD documentation.
       Steve is looking into automatic provisioning of VM's running
       Jenkins in the FreeBSD cluster using Ansible.</li>

    <li>Craig Rodrigues will be running a Continuous Testing working
       group at the FreeBSD Devsummit in Ottawa on May 15, 2014.
       Craig will also give a Jenkins presentation on May 17, 2014.
       Craig is interested in working with Julio Merino to
       integrate Jenkins and Kyua.  Craig and Julio have exchanged
       some e-mails about this on the freebsd-testing list.</li>

    <li>Steve Wills maintains the devel/jenkins-lts port.
       Steve has implemented several builds at jenkins.FreeBSD.org
       which detect commits to the FreeBSD ports repository, and then
       builds the ports tree using poudriere.</li>
    </ul>

  </body>

  <help>
    <task>Obtain certificates for LDAP and web servers, to replace self-signed certificates.</task>
    <task>Set up more Jenkins builds of FreeBSD src on different branches and with different configurations.</task>
    <task>Set up more Jenkins builds of FreeBSD ports on different FreeBSD versions.</task>
    <task>Integrate with Kyua, so that Jenkins can run Kyua tests,
          and report the results directly in the native Jenkins web UI
          where test results are reported.</task>
    <task>Write scripts which can take a Jenkins build of FreeBSD, and boot
          the results in a bhyve VM or on real hardware.</task>
    <task>Fix libpam4j on FreeBSD.</task>
    <task>Continuous Testing working group at Devsummit on May 15, 2014</task> 
    <task>Jenkins presentation at BSDCan on May 17, 2014</task> 
  </help>
</project>
